Guide to the International Brotherhood of Teamsters Training & Development Department records, 1986-2009 IBT0011
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
IBT Training and Development Department records
1907-2010
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
International Brotherhood of Teamsters, Chauffeurs, Warehousemen, and Helpers of America
IBT0011
3 Linear Feet
This collections contains the records of the International Brotherhood of Teamsters Training & Development department dating from 1986-2009.
Arrangement
Organized into 3 series: Departmental Records, Teamsters Leadership Academy, and Stewards Training Publications and Seminar Materials. Files are organized in the order in which they were recieved.
Biographical / Historical
The IBT Training & Development Department was formed in 2005 as part of an organization-wide restructuring. Its predecessor was the Education Department established in 1982. From 1978 to 1982 training was undertaken by the Research and Education Department. The Training & Development Department designs programs and materials to train IBT officers, staff, stewards and members in a variety of areas of labor relations. The department sponsors the Teamster Leadership Academy which provides training in collective bargaining, organizing, political action and union administration.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred by the International Brotherhood of Teamsters, 2012 [2012.007]
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains meeting minutes, subject files, programs, brochures, photographs, and reports of the Training and Development Division of the International Brotherhood of Teamsters, previously known as the Education Department. The material dates from 1986-2009. These are the records of the Training and Development Division after the restructuring of the International Brotherhood of Teamsters, as well as photographs and event materials dated previous to that restructuring.
The Training and Development Division is primarily responsible for education local unions and their leaders on such matters as: union administration, collective bargaining, membership mobilization, effective communications, and leadership.
Labor unions -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Labor unions; Labor
- Departmental Records, 1907-2008; Series 1
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains administrative files, event planning records, correspondence, partnerships, and programs administered by the Training and Development Division. These materials are dated from 2004 to 2008.
  - Trustees' Education Conference, 2004; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Teamsters Local Union 628 Shop Stewards Seminar, 19-20 April 2008; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Trustees Planning Team, 2004-2005; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Partnerships with Universities, undated; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Building Members' Solidarity, undated; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - New Member Orientation Programs, undated; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Teamsters Trustees Education Program-"Building Teamster Power"-Detroit, MI, March 14, 2006; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Teamsters Trustees Education Program-"Protecting Teamster Benefits"-Detroit, MI, March 15, 2006; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Boston Credential to the Fifth Annual Convention of the IBT and Photogragh, 1907; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - "What Local 743 Means to Me" - Steward Interview Transcripts, 1968 - 1969; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - How to Win Strikes, prepared by Local 115, 1991; IBT0011 Series 1 (Box SHARED Box 31, Folder 2)
- Teamsters Leadership Academy (TLA), 1986-2010; Series 2
  Organized into 3 subseries: Records, Events, and Photographs.
  This series contains administrative files, case studies, programs, handouts, agendas, conference materials, and photographs. These materials are dated from 1986 to 2009. The Teamsters Leadership Academy is a leadership program that was established in 1986 to provide Local Union leaders with the information and skills they need to address an ever-changing workplace and labor relations environment. The Teamsters Leadership Academy is held both in Washington, D.C. and in the regions.
  - Records, 1998-2005; Series 2 Subseries 1
    This subseries includes printed flyers and worksheets, administrative files, case studies, and subject files pertaining to the administration of the Teamsters Leadership Academy. The materials are dated from 1998 to 2005.
    - Handouts, 1998-2005; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Office Managers and Administrative Staff, 2003; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Information, Skills, and Strategies, 2004; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Collective Bargaining, 2005; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Arbitration Case Study, undated; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Easyinfo.leader; a CD for Teamster Officers and Business Representatives, undated; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 4, Cd 14)
    - Teamsters: Driving America's Future, undated; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 4, Cd 10, Cd 9)
    - Miscellanous-Sally Payne Seminars & Teamsters Leadership Academy Agendas, 1985-2010; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - "The Teamster Story: A History Worth Preserving" Agenda & History Packet, October 12-14, 2010; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - The Duty of Fair Representation, Undated; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box Shared Box 36, Folder 2)
    - El Procedimiento para la Presentacion de Reclamaciones, Undated; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box Shared Box 36, Folder 3)
  - Events, 1986-2000; Series 2 Subseries 2
    The materials of this series include planning documents, brochures, agendas, and conference packets. They range in date from 1986 to 2000, and offer a glimpse into the nature of events organized as part of the Teamsters Leadership Academy program during that time.
    - Teamsters Leadership Academy, January 13-17 1986, Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Teamsters Leadership Academy, March 22-26, 1993 [2/2], 1993 March 22-26; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Teamsters Leadership Academy, March 22-26, 1993 [1/2], 1993 March 22-26; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Local Education Coordinators Conference, February 21-25, 1994, 1994 February 21-25; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Stewards Seminar Checklist, 1995; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - New Officers, 1995 April 19-21; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - George Meany Center [1/2], 1995; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - George Meany Center [2/2], 1995; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Teamsters Leadership Academy, May 8-12, 2000, 8 May - 12 May 2000; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Photographs, 1993-2010; Series 2 Subseries 3
    This series includes photographic materials taken during the course of Teamsters Leadership Academy events throughout the country. This material is dated from 1993 to 2009 and includes significant undated and unidentified material.
    - 93-99, Norma, Guard Teamsters Office, Terry & Linda Teamsters Office, Diane and David West 2000, Barbara Joe, at her Mother and Danny, 1993-1999; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 4, Cd 13)
    - Teamsters Leadership Academy, May 8-12, 1995, Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Strike Against Overnite, 2000; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Teamsters Local #71, (Charlotte, NC); Stewards Seminar, Sam Carter "Postcards from the Field", 2000; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Teamsters Local #77; Stewards Seminar, 2000 June; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Organizing the Teamsters Leadership Academy, 2001; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 4, Cd 13)
    - Teamsters Local #911 (Palm Springs), Public Employees Public School System, 2001; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Teamsters Local #421; STW Photos, Mock Collective Bargaining Program, 2001 February 21; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 2, Cd 5)
    - Terrell Junior High School Career Day, 2001 April 26; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 4, Cd 13)
    - Buffalo Soldiers, 2002; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 4, Cd 11)
    - Dr. George DiPilato, President of Teamsters Local #502, Reads "Click, Clack, Moo: Cows that Type" at Alexander Adaire Elementary School, 2002; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Teamsters Local #115; Skills For Tomorrow Project, 2002 May 14-17; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Teamsters Local #745; Stewards Seminar, 2003; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Groundhog Shadow Job Program, 2003; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 4, Cd 13)
    - TLA Registrants, 2003 September; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 4, Cd 13)
    - Caitlin Gabel School Visit, Education Photos, 2004 February 13; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 2, Cd 7)
    - Education Photos, 2004 April 24; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 2, Cd 8)
    - International Brotherhood of Teamsters, June 14, 2004, 2004 June 14; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 2, Cd 2)
    - Steward Seminar, 2004 September 25; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 2, Cd 5)
    - Jim Zack (Ohio guys), Sally, Mike Cunningham, Tish Wilson, Baker, Convention, 2006; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 4, Cd 13)
    - Career Fair, November 09, 2009 November; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 4, Cd 13)
    - Ray Isner, Director of Organizing, Teamsters Local #631, undated; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Teamsters Canada #79; Niagara Falls, Ontario, undated; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Teamsters Local #86; Stewards Seminar, with Joey Spradley, President., undated; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Unidentified event, undated; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - JC 65 (Springfield, IL); Training Program, undated; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Teamsters Local #170 (Worcester, MA), Buffalo Soldiers, undated; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Department Baby Shower, undated; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Teamsters Local #741; Stewards Preparing for Case Hearings, undated; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Unidentified Event, undated; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Slides, undated; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Teamsters Local #82, undated; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Unidentified Photos, undated; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - AM West CSR Training, undated; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Teamsters Leadership Academy Pictures, undated; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 2, Cd 1)
    - IBT Women's Conference, undated; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 2, Cd 3)
    - Steward Training, Buffalo, undated; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 2, Cd 4)
    - Unidentified Photos [1/5], undated; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Unidentified Photos [2/5], undated; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Unidentified Photos [3/5], undated; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Unidentified Photos [4/5], undated; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Unidentified Photos [5/5], undated; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Teamsters Local #2000 NWA Rep Training & OGR, undated; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 4, Cd 12)
    - Truck Pictures, undated; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 4, Cd 13)
    - Stewards, James P. Hoffa, Arbitration TLA, 2010; Series 2, Subseries 3 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Picture of Unidentified Stewards, ND; Series 2, Subseries 3 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Stewards' Training Publications and Seminar Materials, 1961-2010; Series 3
  This series represents the range of steward training activities undertaken by the Training & Development Department.
  This series is arranged by subject.
  - "How to Write a Union Flyer", undated; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - "IBT Focus on Negotiations" and "Union Administration" booklets, undated; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - "Chronology of Labor History and Glossary of Labor Terms", 1988; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - "Brief History of the International Brotherhood of Teamsters" draft & untitled note, undated; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - "How to Win Strikes" Manual, October, 2001; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Teamsters Fair Trade Manual-Trade, 2010; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - "Bargaining Manual"; "Information for the Teamster Steward"; and "Developing a Steward System", 2010; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Manuals: "Time Management"; "Running an Effective Union Office"; and "Better Union Meetings", 2010; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - "The Organizing Manual", 2010; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - "Building a Strong Union: A Training Workbook for Teamster Stewards", 2010; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Miscellanous-Negotiations Excersizes, Guides, and Procedures for Stewards (Local 174 & 954), undated; Series 3 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Teamsters Local Union No. 1224-Steward Training Seminar-Wilmington, Ohio, February 6-8, 2001; Series 3 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Teamsters Joint Council No. 46-Steward Seminar-Cheektowaga, New York, Octber 5, 2001; Series 3 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Teamsters Local Union No. 249/636-Steward Seminar- Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, February 28, 2004; Series 3 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Teamsters Local Union No. 710-Steward Seminar- Chicago, Illinois, April 16-17, 2005; Series 3 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Teamsters Local Union No. 710-Effective Communications for Teamsters Stewards- Chicago, Illinois, April 17, 2005; Series 3 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Teamsters Local Union No. 745- Stewards Seminar- Dallas, Texas, June 18, 2005; Series 3 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Teamsters Local Union No. 127- Stewards Seminar- Auburn, Massachusetts, September 17, 2005; Series 3 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Teamsters Local Union No. 744- Stewards Seminar- Chicago, Illinois, November 19, 2005; Series 3 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - 2008 Holiday Party Compact Discs (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Teamster Stewards Make A Difference Manual, Undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Steward Training Workbook, Undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Protecting Those Who Serve Compact Disc, Undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Local 386 - Shop Stewards Seminar, October 4, 2008; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Local 495 - Shop Steward Guide and Membership Guide, 1996; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Local 743 - Stewards Manual and Work Kit, 1961; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Local 769 - Shop Steward's Guide, Miami, FL, 1970; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - On the Same Team: The Joe Nero Story, 2021; Series 3 (Box Shared Box 35, Folder 1)
  - Thunder, Lightning, and the Proud History of the Teamster Insignia, Circa 2018; Series 3 (Box Shared Box 35, Folder 2)
  - The Steward's Quick Guide for Welcoming New Members, Undated; Series 3 (Box Shared Box 36, Folder 4)
  - Teamster Basics - Frequently Asked Questions, Undated; Series 3 (Box Shared Box 36, Folder 5)
  - Weingarten Rights - Worker's Right to Union Representation [English and Spanish], Undated; Series 3 (Box Shared Box 36, Folder 6)